Guide to the New-York Historical Society Bequests, Gifts & Related Matters Record Group 1852-1992 NYHS-RG 16
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society bequests, gifts and related matters
1852-1992
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 16
9.54 Linear feet in 20 document boxes and 1 record carton
The New-York Historical Society bequests, gifts & related matters record group (NYHS-RG 16) primarily includes records concerning estates in which N-YHS was named as a beneficiary. Most of these instances resulted in N-YHS receiving museum objects, manuscripts, books, or other items or a financial legacy. The record group also includes files of some donations of objects and funds from donors during their lifetimes, as well as some purchases. The record group includes files on some of the most important patrons and objects in N-YHS's history.
Arrangement Note
The record group is organized in four series, three of which are restricted.
Series I. Bequests to Circa 1960 (1852-1986)
Series II. Bequests from Circa 1960-1982 (1927-1984) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2033
Series III. Bequests from Circa 1983-1988 (1953-1990) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2039
Series IV. Bequests from Circa 1989-1992 (1964-1992) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2043
Access Restrictions
Series I is open to qualified researchers. N-YHS generally restricts the records of the Board and the Executive Office, and certain other related records, for fifty years following the conclusion of the tenure of a President and CEO (formerly, Director). Accordingly, Series II, III, and IV are restricted until 2033, 2039, and 2043, respectively.
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives).
Though this bequests, gifts & related matters record group (NYHS-RG 16) includes extensive and substantive content, there are several other record groups that include files concerning N-YHS acquisitions. These are as follows:
The Collection Accession Registers (NYHS-RG 15) include lists of donations and purchases from the 1840s to 1962, though they can be inconsistent in their coverage and detail.
The New-York Historical Society management committee records (NYHS-RG 1) includes minutes and so-called "official papers," both of which include reference to acquisitions.
General Correspondence (NYHS-RG 2) includes acquisitions, among many other topics.
The Museum Department Records (NYHS-RG 20) and Library Department Records (NYHS-RG 21) include acquisition records, principally for the twentieth century.
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society bequests, gifts & related matters record group (NYHS-RG 16) primarily includes records concerning estates in which N-YHS was named as a beneficiary. Most of these instances resulted in N-YHS receiving museum objects, manuscripts, books, or other items or a financial legacy. In some instances, N-YHS was named as a residuary legatee or specified conditions needed to be met to receive the bequest. In yet other instances, N-YHS renounced the bequest.
In addition to bequests, the series also includes records of some donations of objects and funds from donors during their lifetimes, as well as of items placed on deposit with N-YHS. Some purchases are also documented in the series. The files most commonly hold correspondence, wills and codicils or abstracts of same, Surrogate Court notices and filings, and receipts. Many files also hold inventories, appraisals, agreements related to purchases, deposits or other transactions, and other documents.
The record group includes files on some of the major patrons and objects in N-YHS's history, including the Beekmans, Belknaps, Thomas J. Bryan, Crawford's sculpture The Indian, the Gallatin family, Cass Gilbert drawings, the Livingstons, Katharine Prentis Murphy, James Lenox's Nineveh sculptures, Katherine R. Rogers, the Thompson family, and many others. The container list includes a detailed inventory of the files.
Bequests; Legal documents.; Letters (correspondence); Wills.; Acquisitions (Libraries) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Courts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Lawyers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Libraries -- Gifts, legacies.; Museums -- Acquisitions -- New York (State) -- New York.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.
- Series I. Bequests to Circa 1960, 1852-1986; 5.42 Linear feet in 13 document boxes
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series includes records of bequests and other gifts from 1852 to about 1960. Given that every file in the series represents a completely different matter and that the files span about 100 years of donations, the subject content of each file is noted in the container list. Many of the files include rich documentation including that for many acquisitions important in N-YHS's history, among them gifts and/or bequests from Thomas J. Bryan, Gerard Beekman (family coach), Waldron Phoenix Belknap, Jr. and his mother, Rey Hutchings Belknap, the Gallatin family, John Divine Jones, the Robert Livingston family, Pirie MacDonald, and Katharine Prentis Murphy and her brother, Edmund Astley Prentis. The series includes extensive documentation of the large financial legacy received from the Thompson family estate that was used to expand the Central Park West building and N-YHS's programs and staff in 1937-38. Among the major accessions documented in the series are Thomas Crawford's sculpture The Indian (from Frederic de Peyster), the drawings of architect Cass Gilbert, ancient Nineveh sculptures (from James Lenox), and bronze models by sculptor John Rogers (from his daughter, Katherine). The series includes some purchases, such as the Robert Bracklow photographs from Alexander Alland, portrait paintings from artist DeWitt Lockman, the Nadelman folk art collection, and Leonidas Westervelt's Jenny Lind collection.
  In addition to acquisitions from individuals, the series also holds files on some institutions that donated or deposited their records to N-YHS, or considered the possibility. Among these is the 1938 proposal, eventually declined, of the donation of the collections of the Marine Museum of the City of New York to N-YHS. Other institutions include, among others, the Naval History Society; the Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the U.S., Commandery of the State of New York; the Protestant Episcopal Church in the United States; and the Sons of Rhode Island in New York.
  Some files include subjects tangentially related to the bequest or gift itself. These include the exhibition of the Belknap Collection in 1950; the installations of the Prentis-Murphy Collection (1950s) and the Nadelman Folk Art Collection (circa 1940); the 1912 New York State court case concluding that N-YHS was an educational institution for the purpose of exemption from a transfer tax on bequests (De Peyster, C. Augusta file); the financial records for production of the first volume paid from the John Divine Jones Fund; and the successful effort to overturn the directive in the will of Augustus Van Horne Stuyvesant, Jr. to destroy much of his property. Generally the cut-off for this series is 1960, but there are later documents in the series that are included as they relate to the earlier transaction.
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged in alphabetical order by name. The names were generally taken from the original folders, and typically are the name of an estate, donor, lender, seller, or other source of an object or funds. Some names, though, refer to the item received.
  - Statement of Legacies and Estates, circa 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Appears to be a list of pending wills and estates in which N-YHS was named as a legatee, as of circa 1935 with annotated updates to circa 1941.
  - Abeel, George, 1912-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Bequest of Abeel and Duyckinck family portraits and funds for their care. File includes photographs of the portraits (accessions 1918.1, 1918.2, 1918.6, 1918.8, 1918.9, 1918.19).
  - Adams, Helen, 1901, 1931-1933, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Principally includes documents related to George T. and William G. Mortimer (obituaries, photographs, extract from George's will, and George's honorable discharge from the 71st Regiment of New York (1901). Also includes the printed "Memoir of Cyrus Cornelius Adams."
  - Althause, Carrie, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Surrogate Court notices only.
  - Alland, Alexander, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Purchase of Robert L. Bracklow and Jacob A. Riis photographs. Offers of other images, including about 430 by Jessie Tarbox Beals.
  - Amen Corner Benches (5th Avenue Hotel), 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Donation of two benches formerly in the 5th Avenue Hotel.
  - Anthony, Theodore V.W., 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Bequest of coat-of-arms of Allard Anthony.
  - Arkenburgh, Weber Hill, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Bequest of pitchers, glass, and other museum objects, and woodcuts.
  - Aymar, Benjamin, 1933, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Bequest of a portrait of Aymar's grandfather of the same name. An unrelated reference to the Thompson estate matter is included in one of the letters in the file.
  - Bailey, Rosalie F., 1947-1953, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Bequest of Theodorus Bailey's N-YHS membership to his daughter, Rosalie. Loan (L.1953.2) of portrait of Nathaniel Platt Bailey and return (1973).
  - Baldwin, Margaret Bayard, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Bequest of tea set.
  - Bancker, Adrian (Portrait), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Bequest by George S. de Groot of two Bancker family portraits.
  - Bar Association of the City of New York, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Indefinite loan to N-YHS of portraits of Mayor Yates and the Randolphs.
  - Barker, Ellen Frye, 1939, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Bequest of various genealogical papers.
  - Beatty, William Gedney, 1918, 1925, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Bequest of books, pamphlets, and pie crust table formerly owned by Philip Schuyler. The file includes 1918 correspondence and invoice concerning the table's provenance.
  - Beekman, Gerard (2 folders), 1909-1913, 1919, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    Includes a copy of the certificate of incorporation of the Beekman Family Association and deeds of gifts to it from Gerard Beekman, and related documents (1909-1910, 1913); gift of Beekman to N-YHS of the family coach, room linings and parts of the entrance from the Turtle Bay house (1911), with funds for the care of the objects; notice of probated will (1919); lists of Beekman family objects at N-YHS (1946) and related documents.
  - Belknap Collection (6 folders), 1944-1963 (Box 1, Folder 18-23)
    Includes gifts, bequests, and loans from Waldron Phoenix Belknap, Jr. (died 1949) and his mother, Rey Hutchings Belknap (died 1960), and other correspondence related to particular objects. Includes correspondence and other matter related to the 1950 exhibition of the collection. Includes the loan receipts and other documents, both from Mrs. Belknap and various institutions, for the 1955 exhibition of colonial portraits derived from English mezzotint engravings.
  - Belmont, Perry, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Gift of silver dinner service formerly owned by Commodore Matthew C. Perry.
  - Bement, Edward, 1932-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Financial legacy.
  - Benet, Lillian, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Provisional gift, subject to release, of family jewelry and manuscript.
  - Benson, Arthur D., 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Bequest of silver tea set.
  - Benson, Egbert, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Concerns N-YHS's contribution to the Prospect Cemetery Association Trust Fund for the care of the grave of Egbert Benson.
  - Bishop, Ann E., 1925 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes only an unsigned copy of an inheritance tax-related deposition.
  - Blair, Natalie K. (Mrs. J. Insley), 1947-1953, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Bequest of china, glass, and other objects.
  - Bolton, Ethelind, 1942, 1946, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Bequest of portrait paintings that had been donated to N-YHS by Bolton during her lifetime.
  - Boucher, William James, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Surrogate Court notice of probated will only.
  - Boyd, Annie M., 1952, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Renunciation of bequest of needlework.
  - Boyd, James, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Gift of about 400 etchings of New York by various artists.
  - Brazer, Esther S. & Clarence W., 1948, 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Consideration and refusal to purchase the Brazer property, known as Innerwyck, under the will's provisions.
  - Bruce, Matilda W., 1908 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Bequest of a painting by Huntington, a painting by T. Birch, and a gold medal.
  - Bryan, Thomas J. (3 folders), 1852-1853, 1867-1871 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
    Gift and bequest of Bryan's art collection. The folders include an 1852-53 scrapbook of clippings about the collection, the original indenture by which the collection was donated to N-YHS, with inventory attached; drafts of the agreement; a statement from Bryan's heirs (circa 1870) relinquishing claims; and the printed proceedings announcing Bryan's death (1870).
  - Bullard, Robert L., 1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Gift of military uniforms, flags, and the like.
  - Burr, Tunis B., 1931, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Bequest of a Bixby edition of the Aaron Burr private journal.
  - Campau, Melancton Woolsey, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Bequest of three portrait paintings.
  - Cassidy, Arthur R., 1957 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Bequest of candlesticks, prints, manuscripts, and other items.
  - Child, Edward B. (2 folders), 1895-1906, 1932-1948 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    Bequest of a watch and and a small financial legacy. Includes indenture conveying one lot for burial in Woodlawn Cemetery (1895) and a drawing of the marker. Includes various title abstracts and other documents related to real estate ownership at 849 East 169th Street in Morrisania (1905-06).
  - City History Club of New York, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Permanent loan of McGown's drum, belt, and ammunition case, and three Revolutionary War objects.
  - Clark, Henry A., 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Clarkson, Helen S., 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Bequest of a portrait painting of Augustus Jay.
  - Cofer, Luisita Leland, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Bequest of a table from the captain's cabin of the U.S.S. Constitution.
  - Cooper-Hewitt Family Costumes, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Indefinite loan from N-YHS to Brooklyn Museum of gowns, wraps and hats.
  - Cooper Union, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Long term loan of paintings by Durand, West, Hicks, Alexander, and de Madrazo, and of wax model by Saint-Gaudens.
  - Cornell, William A., 1910 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Surrogate Court summons only, concerning estate of J. Marcus Booman.
  - Cox, Isabella Vache, 1925-1931, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Bequest of jewelry, books, and financial legacy. Also includes a detailed inventory of items presented, presumably as gifts to N-YHS, by Isabella and Mary E. Cox in 1925, 1926, and 1931.
  - Crawford, Thomas, 1874-1875 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Gift from Frederic de Peyster of Crawford's sculpture The Indian. Also includes documentation related to de Peyster's purchase of the statue from Crawford's estate.
  - Crosby, Edward Nicoll, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Surrogate Court notice only.
  - Cruikshank, Edwin A., 1912-1919, 1925-1929 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Loan of over 500 prints (1912-19) and subsequent gift by Cruikshank's daughter, Susie Cruikshank Snyder.
  - Cryder, Henry C., 1958, 1960, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Renunciation of bequest of a gold nugget on a bar pin.
  - Cushman, James Stewart, 1952, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Daggett, Windsor P., 1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Surrogate Court's notice only
  - Davis, Flora F. & Joseph B., 1928, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Return to Davis's estate of various objects previously loaned to N-YHS by her brother, Joseph B. Davis.
  - De Forest, Louis Effingham, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Bequest of various objects, manuscripts, etc. related to the history and genealogy of the De Forest family.
  - De Peyster, C. Augusta, 1907, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Financial gift. The file also includes documents related to a financial legacy from De Peyster and to the related New York State court case concluding that N-YHS was an educational institution for the purpose of exemption from a transfer tax on bequests.
  - De Peyster, Emily M., 1918 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Includes Surrogate Court notices only.
  - De Windt Desk, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Purchase from Ella C. Sneden of desk used by Washington in de Windt house in Tappan, NY, in 1780.
  - Delafield, Edward C., 1954 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Financial gift establishing the Edward C. Delafield Fund.
  - Demott, Helen B., 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Gift of a Sheraton (or Hepplewhite) sideboard.
  - Dexter, Henry (3 folders), 1910-1938 (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
    Renunciation of bequest of Dexter's library and family photographs and portraits. The file includes no documentation concerning Dexter's contributions to N-YHS during his lifetime, including those he made for building construction.
  - Dey, Richard Varick, 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Dod, Isabel G., 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Bequest of silver inkstand and candlesticks.
  - Dorman, Adriana Rapalje, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Bequest of two portrait paintings.
  - Doscher, William, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Renunciation of bequest of portrait paintings.
  - Dresser, Catherine M., 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Bequest of a crayon portrait of New York City mayor Stephen Allen.
  - Duane, William North, 1944-1946 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Bequest of the diary of James Duane and other manuscripts.
  - DuBois, Mary Constance, 1955, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Bequest of furniture, silver, jewelry, manuscripts, and other items.
  - Dunn, Cleveland A., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Bequest of genealogical and other personal historical records.
  - Durand, Frederic F., 1903, 1921, 1931, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Durell, Mary S., 1899 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Bequest of Judge Durell's volumes of clippings, notes, correspondence, and other manuscripts.
  - Eames, Wilberforce, 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Bequest of imprints, daguerreotypes and other photographs, two medals, and other objects.
  - Eliot, Jr., Ellsworth, 1945-47, 1950, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Contingent bequest of books and manuscripts related to the Eliot family (1940s-50) and proposed loan of same to N-YHS by heirs (1963).
  - Eliot, Walter Graeme, 1930-1934 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Bequest of portraits.
  - Ellis, Anne Middleton (Mrs. Augustus Van Horne), 1946-1952 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Bequest of a miniature of Ellis, with case, painted by Lydia Field Emmet.
  - Evans, Mai Campbell Barrows, 1940, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    No bequest; Waiver of citation in probate proceedings.
  - Fairchild, Helen L., 1874, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Relates to a portrait group.
  - Federal Hall Desk & Lectern, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Statement by Edward C. Taylor of provenance through the family of Jared Sparks of desk and eagle.
  - Francis, Claude de la Roche, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Decree denying probate.
  - Gallatin, Albert Eugene, 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Bequest of furniture and other objects purportedly formerly owned by Albert Gallatin (1761-1849). File includes notes concerning provenance of some items.
  - Gallatin Papers, 1880-1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Gifts of papers, books, medals, and other objects in 1880 associated with Albert Gallatin and the Gallatin family, with gifts in later years, and related matters.
  - Geissenhainer, Frederick W., 1954 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Gibbs, George, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Bequest of portrait of Elizabeth Wolcott Gracie by Trumbull.
  - Gilbert, Cass, 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Gift from Emily Gilbert of Gilbert's drawings, papers, and other matter, with financial contributions.
  - Gilman, Charles W., 1941-1943 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Bequest of a watch and a letter from Lafayette.
  - Gitelson, M. Leo (5 folders), 1955-1968 (Box 4, Folder 8-12)
    Underwriting of a microfilming project. Underwriting of a cooperative effort to collect photostat images of broadsides (The Bailey Gitelson Library of Americana). File includes copies of various issues of "The Chronicle" and "The Magnet," publications of the Gitelson-Kamaiko Foundation. Other topics are also included in the files, including an attempt by Gitelson's daughter, Susan Aurelia Gitelson, with N-YHS's support, to establish an essay contest at Barnard College and Gitelson's attempt (declined) to publish an article in N-YHS's Quarterly.
  - Gordon, Grace Hyde, 1919-1920 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Purchase from estate of paintings, including one by Rembrandt Peale, jewelry, table cloths, and other objects.
  - Gosman, Richard A., 1946 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Bequest of furniture, weapons, and other objects.
  - Grider Powder Horn Drawings, circa 1950s? (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Includes an inventory of the Grider collection prepared by N-YHS with an introduction referring to its provenance.
  - Griswold, Rufus W., 1893 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Petition related to William McC. Griswold's application for letters of administration in connection with estate of Rufus Griswold, and property apparently held by N-YHS.
  - Grosvenor, Seth, 1858 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Financial legacy. Includes a certified copy of Grosvenor's will and Luther Bradish's special committee report to N-YHS concerning the bequest.
  - Harbord, James G., 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Bequest of photographs, military and other objects, correspondence, and other items.
  - Harper, Mabel Herbert, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Financial legacy for book purchases (Harper Funds).
  - Hawley, Alan R., 1938 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Bequest of picture, trophy, plaque, brevet, scrapbooks, and a financial legacy.
  - Hedden, Edward Harold, 1936, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Bequest of family records, geneological and other books, insignia, emblems, and case for them.
  - Heiser, Rosalie M., 1940-1941 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Bequest of a portrait by Jarvis of DeWitt Clinton.
  - Hoes, Roswell Randall, 1923, 1930, 1940, 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Deposit of collection with N-YHS (1923-24) by Hoes's widow, Rose Governeur Hoes, and return of material (1930), except for John Vanderlyn letters, which were donated by Rose Hoes. Gift later determined to be invalid and Vanderlyn letters returned to heirs (1950-54).
  - Hoffman, Eugene, 1902-1903 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Hoffman, Malvina, 1951-1963, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Gifts from the artist of plaster busts and other sculptures (1950s, 1960s?). Offer (declined) of indefinite loan of large bas reliefs (1957). File includes reference to a bequest of busts and to a 1950s exhibition of Hoffman's gifts to N-YHS.
  - Holgate, Ella H., 1918 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Hood, Anna, 1944, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Bequest of portrait painting, pastels, lithograph, and silhouettes.
  - Horton, Roberta Benton, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Acknowledgement from Horton of return of miniatures by John Watson loaned to N-YHS.
  - Hoyt, Virginia Scott, 1937-1939 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Bequest of sword of General Winfield Scott.
  - Hudson River Chain Links, 1880, 1924, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)